[Ebina-san lived in the pond. He kept his promise forever.]
[The evil land shark Ibaraki family plots to turn the pond into a golf course.]
["If You're a Man, Try the Swordfish!"]
(新八)きた！
Hooked one!
うぉっ！
こりゃ 間違いなく大物ですよ！
Oh! It's definitely a big one.
ぐぅっ… おらぁっ！
You're not getting away.
うっ… なんだ ｺｲﾂ！
What's this?
やっぱ 天人が来てから
地球の生態系も➡
Since the Amanto came, the Earth's ecosystem has gotten so...weird.
おかしくなってますね｡
(銀時)いいから ﾊﾞｹﾂ入れとけ｡
Never mind that. Put it in the bucket.
えぇっ！ これ 食べんの？
What?! You're going to eat this?!
Of course I am.
あったりめえだろ｡
ｱﾝｺｳしかり 納豆しかり➡
Anko's tasty and Natto's tasty, right?
見た目がｸﾞﾛいもんほど
食ったら うめえんだよ｡
The more grotesque it looks, the better it tastes when you eat it.
Even an ugly a woman always has one or two good points.
どんなﾌﾞｻｲｸにも いいところの
１つや２つ あるもんだ｡
Gin-chan, Gin-chan!
(神楽)銀ちゃん 銀ちゃん！
(神楽)これ…
すごいの釣れたｱﾙ！ 見て見て！
I caught a huge one. Look, look!
Ow-ow-ow-ow-ow!
(海老名)ｱﾀﾀﾀﾀ…！
…あれ？ 痛くないかも？
Huh? Maybe it doesn't hurt?
あっ やっぱ痛い！ ｱﾀﾀﾀ…！
No, it does hurt! Ow-ow-ow!
ねぇねぇ これも食べられるｱﾙか？
Say, can we eat it, too?
(海老名)あぱぁっ!!
あぁ～ 夕食～！
My dinner!
今 見たことは 忘れろ｡ いいな？
Forget what you saw just now, okay?
Gin-san, wasn't that a kappa?
[Kappa, A.K.A. water imp, a mythical water creature]
銀さん…
今の ｶｯﾊﾟじゃありませんでした？
んなもん いるわけねえだろ｡
No such thing.
あれだよ｡ 池に住んでる
ただの ﾊｹﾞたおっさんさ｡
It was just, you know, a regular bald old dude who lives in the pond.
池に住んでる時点で
ただのおっさんじゃねえよ！
Just the fact that he lives in the pond makes him not a "regular old dude."
And besides, he was green.
それに なんか 緑色でしたよ？
それは…｡ あれだよ ｱﾙｺｰﾙ依存症｡
That's because...You know...He's got an alcohol addiction.
ｱﾙｺｰﾙに そんな成分あったら
酒なんて 誰も飲まんわ！ …ん？
Nobody'd drink sake if alcohol did that to them!!
You bastards broke my glasses, dammit!
ﾃﾒｴら ﾒｶﾞﾈ割れちゃったじゃねえか
この野郎｡
Call your parents! I'm making them pay for this!
親に電話しろ！
弁償してもらうからな～！
だぁ～っ！ 出たぁ～っ!!
It's alive!
(神楽/銀時)あぁっ！
待て お前ら～!!
Come back here, you guys!
逃がさん！ 住所と名前を言え～!!
You're not getting away! Tell me your names and addresses!
(銀時/神楽)うわぁっ！
(海老名)おっさんだってなぁ➡
Look, if you had apologized at the start, I wouldn't be so angry.
最初から謝れば
怒んないよ そんなに｡
If you do something wrong, the right thing to do is to apologize.
悪いことをしたら
謝るのが筋だろ？ 違うか？
Am I wrong? Why did you run?
なんで 逃げた？
いや… ｶｯﾊﾟだったから…｡
Well, because you're a kappa.
ｶｯﾊﾟ？ なんじゃ そりゃ｡
A kappa? What's that? Don't try to trick me by talking nonsense!
わけのわからんことを言って
ごまかそうとするな｡
You're the one who's making the least sense!
ｵﾒｴが いちばん
わけわかんねえんだよ｡
What is it about me that doesn't make sense? Tell me, young girl!
おっさんの どこが
わけわかんねえんだ？ この小娘！
And don't call me "you." Call me Ebina-san.
それから ｵﾒｴじゃなくて
海老名さんと呼べ｡
すみませんでした 海老名さん｡
We're sorry, Ebina-san.
I'll break my glasses, too, so please forgive us.
あの ﾎﾞｸも ﾒｶﾞﾈ割りますんで
勘弁してください｡
Good. That was a fine apology, son.
よ～し よく謝ったな ﾎﾞｸ｡
ご褒美の ﾋﾞｽｹｯﾄだ｡
Have a biscuit as a reward.
ありがた迷惑だよ ｺﾝﾁｸｼｮｳ｡
No thanks, you beast!
まぁ 割れたのが
ﾒｶﾞﾈのほうで よかったよ｡
Well, it's a good thing it was only my glasses that broke.
If it had been my dish that broke, this old man would have lost it.
これで ｵﾒｴ もし 皿が割れてたら
さすがのおっさんも ｷﾚてたね｡
お前ら 全員 ﾎﾞｺﾎﾞｺだったよ｡
I'd have beaten you all to a pulp.
いいか？ ｵﾚの皿だけは…
この皿だけは➡
Understand this: nobody lays a finger on this dish.
何人たりとも触れさせ… ぐはっ！
あぁ～っ！
皿 割れた～！
The dish broke!
Oh man! The dish broke!
大変だぁ！ 皿 割れたぞ！
何が大変なのか知らんけど｡
I don't know what's so awful about it, though.
(ｲﾊﾞﾗｷ)あぁ ごめ～ん｡
Oh, I'm so sorry.
I was practicing my golf swing when it just slipped out of my hands!
(ｲﾊﾞﾗｷ)ｺﾞﾙﾌの素振り やってたら
手 滑っちゃった｡
This is why I told you to leave this place.
(ｲﾊﾞﾗｷ)だから
早く出ていけって言ったじゃん｡
This isn't your home. This is my property.
ここは ｱﾝﾀの家じゃない
ｵﾚの土地なんだよ｡
Because I bought this entire area...
ここいら全部
ｵﾚが 買い取ったんだからさぁ｡
やかましいわ！
こちとらなぁ ﾃﾒｴらが➡
Shut up!
I've been living here since back when you were still in your father's jewels!
親父の銀玉に入ってる頃から
ここに住んでんだ！
なんで出てかなきゃならねえ！
Why should I have to leave?!
Stop staring at me! It's embarrassing!
っていうか あんまこっち見んな
恥ずかしいから｡
ちょっ… ｶﾒﾗは勘弁して ﾎﾝﾄ｡
No cameras please. Really.
He's gotten a bit shy after his dish cracked.
皿が割れて ちょっぴりｼｬｲに…｡
What's with that dish, anyway?
っていうか
意味あんのかよ あの皿｡
I plan to build a huge golf course on this land.
(ｲﾊﾞﾗｷ)ここら一帯に
どでかいｺﾞﾙﾌ場 つくりたいのよ｡
それには
この池が ｼﾞｬﾏなんだってば｡
And this pond is in the way!
I'll find you another pond where you can live, so would you please just leave?
(ｲﾊﾞﾗｷ)ｱﾝﾀの住む池なら
他に用意してやるから➡
ここからは出ていってくんない？
(海老名)
そういう問題じゃねえんだよ！
That's not the issue!
ここはなぁ
ｵﾚだけの池じゃねえんだ｡
This pond doesn't belong only to me.
ここは ｱｲﾂの…｡
It's also her...
なんか よく わかんないけど
これ以上 ｵﾚのｼﾞｬﾏするなら➡
I don't really understand you, pal.
But if you're going to cause me any more trouble, you'd better be prepared for what's coming.
それ相応の覚悟は しといてよ｡
You never know when the next golf ball is gonna come flying at you.
どっから ｺﾞﾙﾌﾎﾞｰﾙ飛んでくるか
わかんないよ～｡
There, it's fixed, old man.
ほら 直ったｱﾙよ おっさん｡
(皿が割れる音)
ﾌﾊﾊ！ ﾌﾊﾊ！
…あれ？
Huh?! Did you hear a cracking noise?
今 ﾊﾞﾘﾝっていわなかった？
気のせいですよ｡
It's just your imagination.
おっさんよぉ
引っ越しするなら 手伝うぜ｡
Old man, if you're going to move, we'll help.
It's none of your business, fool!
(海老名)
よけいなお世話だ ﾊﾞｶ野郎｡
あれ 見ろ｡
Look over there.
See that odd-looking island?
(海老名)妙なもんが見えるだろ｡
ありゃ 昔 ｵﾚが乗ってきた船だ｡
That's the spaceship I rode here on a long time ago.
Ebina-san, you're an Amanto?
海老名さん
あなた 天人なんですか？
ｵﾚたちの種族は
清い水がねえと 生きられねえ｡
Our species can't live without clean water.
Long ago, our planet lost all its water in a catastrophic natural disaster.
その昔 ｵﾚたちの星は
天変地異で 水を失い➡
皆 新天地を求め 旅立った｡
We set out to find a new home.
そして ｵﾚがたどりついたのが
この水の星… 地球よ｡
I found my way to this water planet, Earth.
(海老名)たまげたよ～
こんなきれいな星があったなんて｡
I was shocked to find such a lovely planet.
あの頃は
天人も ほとんどいなかったし➡
At the time, there were hardly any Amanto,
so I felt as though I had this jewel all to myself.
宝石 独り占めした気分だった｡
(海老名)だが ｵﾚの姿は➡
But earthlings only saw me as a monster.
地球人にとっちゃ
化け物以外の何者でもねえ｡
迫害され ｵﾚは 池に戻り
孤独に生きるようになった｡
I was persecuted and forced to return to this pond to live in solitude.
人はよぉ
他人の中にいる自分を感じて➡
But you know, you only feel alive when you're connected to other people.
初めて
生きている実感を得るんだ｡
I found a safe place to live...But it was like being dead.
ｵﾚは 生きる場所は得たが
死んでたも同然だったんだ｡
Until I met her, that is...
そう… ｱｲﾂに会うまでは…｡
(海老名)ｿｲﾂは いつのまにか
池のほとりにいたんだ｡
She appeared one day along the pond bank.
She didn't do anything; she just stared out at the water.
何にもせずに ただ ず～っと
池 眺めてたんだよ いつも｡
ｵﾚも 最初は 隠れてたんだが
そのうち ﾊﾞｶらしくなってな…｡
At first, I hid from her, but after a while it just seemed silly.
You there, why do you always just sit there?
((ｵﾒｴ…
いつも そこで 何やってんだ？))
(海老名)娘は ｵﾚを見て
少し驚いたふうだったが…｡
The girl looked at me, and was a bit surprised, but...
((少女:部屋にいても １人だから
つまんなくて…｡
I'm lonely and bored in my bedroom, so I thought, "why not be alone out here?"
どうせなら ここで１人でいようと
思ったんだけど…➡
２人だったんだね))
But there are two of us now.
The girl had a sickness in her lungs.
(海老名)娘は 肺を患っていた｡
人にうつる病だ｡
A contagious disease.
She snuck out of the room where she was kept isolated because no one wanted to be near her.
腫れもの扱いされて
部屋に隔離されてたところを➡
忍んで出てきてたのさ｡
She didn't care who I was; she just wanted someone to talk to.
誰でもいいから
話し相手が欲しかったのさ…➡
ｵﾚも ｱｲﾂもな｡
ｹﾞﾛｯﾊﾟ！
And so did I.
Ever since then, the only time I really felt alive was when I was talking with her.
(海老名)それから
ｱｲﾂと語る時間だけが➡
ｵﾚの生きる時間になった｡
We talked about silly things, but it was fun.
たわいもない話しかしなかったが
楽しかったよ｡
(少女の笑い声)
((少女:おじさんは いいね｡
(海老名)何が？
You're lucky, mister.
How so?
You can swim free in such lovely water.
(少女)こんなきれいな水の中
自由に泳げて…｡
I've been frail since childhood, so I've never been able to swim.
(少女)私 小さい頃から
体 弱かったから➡
泳いだことなんて
一度もないんだ｡
一度でいいから
自由に泳いでみたいよ…➡
Just once, I wish I could swim freely...
透明な世界を｡
In that clear world...
体 治しゃいい｡
Strengthen your body.
That's impossible. I've been like this all my life.
(少女)ﾑﾘよ… もう ずっとだもの｡
(海老名)ﾊﾞｶ野郎
人生は 長いんだぜ｡
Silly girl! Life is long.
ｵﾒｴが 体 治すまで
ここは ｵﾚが守っといてやるよ｡
I'll protect this place until you're strong and healthy.
きれいなままでな｡
I'll keep it just as beautiful as it is now.
だから さっさと 体 治してきな｡
So, hurry up and get well.
わかった｡
All right. It's a promise, mister.
約束だからね おじさん｡
おうよ！))
You bet.
♪♪～
A promise? But that was decades ago.
約束っつったって
何十年前の話だよ｡
さぁ… でも➡
Perhaps. But...
乗ってきた船が
あんなになるくらいですから➡
The ship he came on looks like it's been there a long time.
少なくとも その娘さんは
とっくに…｡
One thing's for sure, that girl is long...
酔狂にも ほどがあるぜ｡
This borders on the insane. I can't go along with this.
つきあいきれねえや｡
Okay! Everything ready? Get to it.
よ～し 準備いいな｡
じゃあ 頼むわ｡
(野島)へ～い！
Right.
ﾌﾌｯ…腐れｶﾞｯﾊﾟ➡
I've just about had it with that rotten kappa.
ｵﾚも もう我慢の限界だよ｡
池ごと 土の下に
埋めちゃうもんね｡
I'm going to bury the entire lake in dirt.
(大西)でも 大丈夫なんですかね？
ｶｯﾊﾟのたたりとか…｡
But are you sure it's okay? What about the kappa's curse?
(ｲﾊﾞﾗｷ)ﾊﾞｶか お前は！
ｶｯﾊﾟなんているわけないだろ｡
You idiot!
There's no kappa! That's just an Amanto.
ありゃ ただの天人だ｡
Man, why do we have to do this in the dead of night?
ったく… 夜中に
なんで こんなこと➡
しなきゃならねえんだ｡
What's going on? It stopped...
なんだぁ おい？ 止まっ…
うわっ！
I'm Saburo, the kappa. Got a cucumber, mister?
私 三郎ｶﾞｯﾊﾟｱﾙ！
おじさん ｷｭｳﾘちょうだい！
(野島の悲鳴)
(手下)なにやってんだ？
野島のﾔﾂ｡
What's going on with Nojima?
Hey, what's going on?
(手下)おい どうした！ ｷｬﾀﾋﾟﾗに➡
Did the bulldozer snag your jewels or something?!
銀玉でも巻き込まれたか!?
次郎ｶﾞｯﾊﾟ 推参！
It is I, Kappa Jiro!
(手下の悲鳴)
んっ？ なにｷﾞｬｰｷﾞｬｰ騒いでんの？
What's with all that screaming?
ｷｬﾀﾋﾟﾗに銀玉でも巻き込まれたか？
Did your jewels get caught in the bulldozer or something?
大西！ ちょっと見てこ… んっ？
Onishi! Take a look at...
大西…？
Onishi...?
(ｲﾊﾞﾗｷのうめき声)
ﾃ… ﾃﾒｴは!?
Wh-Who're you?
蝦夷は洞爺湖から
参上つかまつった｡
I have come from Lake Toya in Ezo.
ｶｯﾊﾟ三兄弟が長男 太郎ｶﾞｯﾊﾟ｡
I am the eldest of the three kappa brothers, Kappa Taro.
この土地から 今すぐ
手ぇ引いてもらおうか？
Leave this property right now, or the kappa's curse will...
さもなくば ｶｯﾊﾟのたたりが…｡
かっ 勘弁してくれ…｡
No...not that!
Kappa, what do you want? Cucumbers, right?
ｶｯﾊﾟといえば なんだ？ ｷｭｳﾘか？
好きなものを言え！
Tell me what you want! I don't have much hair, but I have plenty of money!
ｵﾚは髪の毛は あまりねえが
金だけはあるぞ！
好きなもの… そうさな…｡
What we like? Let's see...
(ｲﾊﾞﾗｷの悲鳴)
甘いものと 酔狂なﾔﾂかな…｡
Sweets, and guys who take things to extremes, I guess.
んだ ﾃﾒｴ また来てたんか？
What? You guys are back?
よう 聞いたぜ｡
I heard...
Seems this land was put up for sale.
この土地
売りに出されたらしいな｡
これでしばらく
大丈夫じゃねえの？
After this, I think you'll be okay for a while.
おう なんか
本物のｶｯﾊﾟが出たらしいぞ｡
Oh, looks like some real kappa appeared.
ｿｲﾂは 怖えな｡
Now that's scary.
ひょっとして お前…｡
Could it be? You...
おっ！ へぇ…
あんなきれいな魚➡
Oh!
So there are beautiful fish like that that living in this pond?
この池にいたんだなぁ｡
Ha-ha. They sure seem to be having a ball!
ﾊﾊｯ 楽しそうに
泳いでらぁ｡
(ｾﾐの鳴き声と風鈴の音)
462.
462…｡
なにそれ…｡
What's that?
The number of people who collapsed this summer from heatstroke.
今年の夏 熱中症で
ぶっ倒れた人の数ですよ｡
ﾏｼﾞでか…｡
Are you serious?
銀さん やっぱｴｱｺﾝ
買いましょうよ｡
Gin-san, let's buy an air conditioner after all.
今年の猛暑は 扇風機だけじゃ
乗り切れませんって これ｡
This year's intense heat is too much to get by with just a senpuki.
[Senpuki = a Japanese electric fan. ]
ﾊﾞｶ言ってんじゃねえよ！
Don't be ridiculous. Where are we going to find that kind of money?
そんな金 どこにあんだい｡
If you have the time to condition our air, learn how to condition your mind.
ｴｱｰをｺﾝﾃﾞｨｼｮﾆﾝｸﾞする
暇があるなら➡
ﾏｲﾝﾄﾞをｺﾝﾃﾞｨｼｮﾆﾝｸﾞする術を覚えろ｡
心頭滅却すれば
南極もまた 北極だよ｡
Suppress your mind to a state of nothingness and even the south pole can be as cool as the north pole.
銀さん 言っとくけど
南極は 南っていってるけど➡
Gin-san, just so you know,
they call it the "south" pole, but that doesn't mean it's always summer there.
別に 常夏じゃないからね…｡
あんっ！ わかってるよ お前｡
Huh? I know that.
南極が常夏の
ﾊﾟﾗﾀﾞｲｽのわけねえだろ｡
There's no way the south pole is an endless summer paradise.
つまり ｵﾚが言いたいのは
心頭滅却しても… あれ？
What I'm trying to say is that even if you suppress your mind to a state of nothingness...
何も変わらないよね｡
Huh? That doesn't change anything, does it?
恥ずかしい…
間違いを隠すために➡
How embarrassing!
You contradicted your own argument just to cover up your error!
持論 捨てやがったよ！
ひどいよ この人➡
You're awful! So much for our argument!
今のやりとりが ﾊﾟｰだよ！
In the first place, try going out on a day like this.
だいたい！
こんな日に 外 出てみろ｡
ｴｱｺﾝ買う前に ﾊﾞﾀﾝｷｭｰだ｡
You'll collapse before you can buy an air conditioner.
こういう日は おとなしく
家でｺﾞﾛｺﾞﾛしてるのに 限るの！
On a day like this, the best thing to do is lay around the house doing nothing.
ﾊｧ… 頼みの綱は扇風機だけか｡
Our only hope is the senpuki...
みんな 大事に使いましょうね｡
Let's all use it with care.
(ｾﾐの鳴き声)
["If You Go to Sleep with the Fan On You'll Get a Stomachache, So Be Careful"]
I can't stand it! What's hot is hot even if I suppress my mind to a state of nothingness.
あ～ やっぱﾀﾞﾒだ…｡
心頭滅却しても 暑いものは暑い！
つうか なんで こんな暑い日に➡
Why do I have to go and buy a senpuki on a hot day like this?
扇風機なんか 買いにいかなきゃ
ならねえんだ｡
腹 立つな！
What a pain in the ass.
This sucks. Maybe I'll switch and buy an air conditioner instead.
腹立つから ｴｱｺﾝに
のりかえてやろうかな…｡
なぁ おっさん いいかな？
What do you say, old man? Should I upgrade to an air conditioner?
ｵﾚ ｴｱｺﾝにのりかえちゃって
いいかなぁ！
Huh? Well, I don't see why not.
(おっさん)えっ？ いや…
まぁ いいんじゃないの？
いいわけねえだろ！
ｴｱｺﾝ買う金なんて どこにあんだ！
That won't do!
Where am I going to find the money to buy an air conditioner?!
よけいな口 はさむな！
Mind your own business!
Why do I have to get totally sweaty to go and buy a machine that makes me cooler?
つうか なんで
涼しくなるためのﾏｼｰﾝを➡
汗だくになって
買いにいかなきゃならねえんだ？
埋蔵金を 埋蔵金で
掘るようなもんじゃねえか？
It's like digging for buried gold with buried gold.
飲む前に飲むような
もんじゃねえか？
Like drinking before drinking.
次の扇風機が 家にきても
とりあえず 無視だな｡
When the next senpuki arrives, I'm going to ignore it.
For three days and three nights, I'm going to let it blow against the wall.
３日３晩 壁に向かって
微風を吹かせ続けてやるよ！
あ～ 腹立つ ﾎﾝﾄ！
ｴｱｺﾝ 買おうっかな？
This really ticks me off. Should I really buy an air conditioner?
あっ でも 金 ねえんだ…｡
But I don't have any money.
(店員)は？ 扇風機？
[Tsukamoto Electric]
Huh? A senpuki?
すみません ｳﾁには
置いてないわ そういうの｡
I'm sorry, we don't have anything like that.
ほら 今の時代 もうｴｱｺﾝでしょ｡
These days, people use air conditioners, you know?
How about it, mister?
(店員)おにいさんもどう？
これを機会に➡
Why not use this opportunity to upgrade to an air conditioner?
ｴｱｺﾝにのりかえたら？
安くしとくから！
I'll make it cheap.
You mean that? Okay, then. Uh...
ﾏｼﾞすか… じゃ お願いします｡
あの お金のほうは これくらいで
なんとかしてほしいんすけど｡
[1000 yen or roughly $10 USD]
Can you sell me one for this much?
Come one, come all! It's our big summer sale!
寄ってらっしゃい
見てらっしゃい！
Huh? Mister?
夏の大売り出しだよ！
あれ？ おじさん!? おかしいぞ｡
That's strange. He won't make eye contact with me anymore.
おじさんが目を合わせて
くれなくなった！ おじさ～ん!!
Mister!
(ｾﾐの鳴き声)
[Nawa Electric]
A senpuki? Nope, nope. Maybe you should try an antique shop?
(店員)扇風機？
おまへん おまへん｡
骨董屋にでも行ったほうが
ええんちゃう？
(ｾﾐの鳴き声)
What? You're using a senpuki in this day and age?!
(店員)なに？ 今どき
扇風機なんて使ってんの!?
(店員)それってやばくない？
軽く やばくない？
Isn't that dangerous? What are you some kind of throwback?
(店員)なにげに やばくな～い？
A senpuki?
(店員)扇風… ぐぁっ！
Ow-ow-ow-ow! What're you doing?! I haven't said anything yet!
あだだだだ！ なにすんの！
まだ 何もしゃべってないのに！
Shut up! You probably don't have one anyway. I know that.
うるせえよ｡ どうせ ねえんだろ｡
わかってんだよ！
もう 裏はとれてんだよ｡
I did some research...at the back alley shops.
裏のお店で 裏はとれてんだよ！
あぁ 腹立つ！ ｲﾗｲﾗする！
Grrr, this is really pissing me off!
あの 青い空までもが 腹立つ！
Even that beautiful blue sky ticks me off! And it's so blue!
あんなに青いのに～！
Why am I soaking with sweat and passed around from store to store just to buy a measly senpuki?!
なんで 扇風機ごとき買うのに➡
こんなに汗だくで たらい回しに
ならなきゃいけねえんだい！
Hey, mister, can I go home now? Can I go home already?
おい おっさん！
帰っていいかな？
ｵﾚ もう 帰っていいかな!?
Huh? I guess it's okay to go home.
(おっさん)えっ… いや
帰っていいんじゃねえのか？
いいわけねえだろ！
I can't do that! I feel like I've been through a sauna!
家は もう蒸し風呂状態なんだよ！
何も知らねえくせに➡
You don't know a thing!
Don't talk like you do!
知ったような口をきくな！
Damn. This is wrong, so wrong.
ｸｿｯ やっぱ おかしい！
おかしいぞ これは！
扇風機 買いにきてんだよ｡
I'm here to buy a senpuki. I came to cool off!
涼しくなるために 来てんだよ
ｵﾚは！
But I'm just getting hotter and hotter!
なのに 暑くなる一方じゃねえか！
あ～ 腹立つ！ ﾎﾝﾄ｡
ｴｱｺﾝにしときゃあ よかった！
It ticks me off!
I really should've gotten an air conditioner!
But I don't' have the money.
あっ でも 金 ねえんだ…｡
[Recycled Goods Shop: Earth Defense Army Base]
My, it's unusual to have a samurai customer. Welcome.
(十徳の娘)あら…
お侍のお客さんとは 珍しいね｡
いらっしゃい｡
扇風機…｡
A senpuki...You have a senpuki, don't you? Get me one!
扇風機 あんだろ｡ 出せよ こら！
ﾌｰｯ…｡
銭封機… 懐かしい名だね｡
A senpuki...How nostalgic.
Where did you hear about it?
ｱﾝﾀ いったい どこから
その名を聞いてきたんだい？
Never mind, hurry and get one for me!
いいから さっさと出せや！
Now hold on. You're the first customer who's come this far.
まぁ 待ちなよ｡
ここまで来たのは
ｱﾝﾀが初めてさね｡
名くらい 聞かせておくれよ｡
At least tell me your name.
なんだ？ 領収書か？
上様でいいよ！
What? Is that for a receipt? Just write "customer."
上様… 立派な名前じゃないか｡
Customer? That's a fine name.
I'll be seeing you, then, Customer!
じゃあ あばよ 上様!!
(銃声)
Whoa!
なななな… なにすんだ このｱﾏ!!
Wh-Wha-What'd you do that for, you freak!
I want to speak with your manager.
Call the manager!
店長～！ 店長を呼べ～!!
離しな！
ｱﾝﾀらのような 悪の組織に➡
Let go of me! I'll never let an evil syndicate like yours have a senpuki!
銭封機は 絶対 渡さないよ!!
What nonsense are you talking about?
なに わけのわかんねえこと
言ってんだ おい！
Calm down. Maybe you're mistaking me for a thief?
落ち着け｡ 強盗か なんかと
勘違いしてんのか？
I just came to buy a senpuki.
ｵﾚは 扇風機を買いにきただけ…｡
(銃声)
Hey! What's the matter...?!
おい どうした…？ げっ！ 血…！
Blood?!
店長～！ 店長を呼べ～!!
Manager! Call the manager!
(悪の組織のﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)ﾌｯﾌｯﾌｯﾌ｡
ついに見つけたぞ…➡
Found it at last.
The sewer rat's nest.
ﾄﾞﾌﾞﾈｽﾞﾐどもの住みかを…｡
We didn't think anyone other than that woman survived.
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)まさか その女以外に
生き残りがいようとは…｡
(手下たち)ﾌｩ～ ﾌｩ～！
But your luck just ran out today,
Earth Defense Army.
だが 今日で
ｷｻﾏらの命運も尽きた…➡
地球防衛軍よ｡
What? Are you talking to me?
Earth Defen...Say what?
ｵﾚのこと言ってんの？
地球… 何？
Don't play dumb, damn you! You're a remnant of the Earth Defense Army!
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)とぼけるな ｷｻﾏ｡
地球防衛軍の生き残りだろうが｡
Earth Defense...?
地球防衛って…｡
I did once build a bookshelf from milk cartons to be nice to the Earth, but...
確かに 牛乳ﾊﾟｯｸで
本棚 作ったり 地球に➡
優しくしたことはあるが…｡
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)ふざけるな！
Don't give me that! Hand over that senpuki right now!
さっさと 銭封機を渡せ！
I get it, you're here to buy a senpuki, too?
ひょっとして あなた方も
扇風機を ご購入に？
なんすか？ 今 ﾚﾄﾛﾌﾞｰﾑか何か？
Is there a retro boom going on or something?
こんなに流行ってるとは
知らなかったっすよ｡
I didn't know they were such a fad.
No wonder I can't buy one.
どうりで 買えねえはずだ｡
I'm not letting...
(娘)銭封機は…➡
anyone have the senpuki...
誰にも渡さないよ…｡
I'll never let you have it!
(娘)ｱﾝﾀらなんかに
絶対 渡さない！
Th-This is...a grena...
こ… これは ばく…｡
(爆発音)
(野次馬たちの騒ぎ声)
(銀時の むせる声)
Why...does this have to happen to me?
なんで… こんな目に遭わなきゃ
ならねえんだ…｡
All I did was come to buy a senpuki.
扇風機 買いにきただけなのに…｡
ｱﾝﾀ 何者か知らないが
悪いﾔﾂじゃなさそうだね…｡
I don't know who you are, but you don't seem to be a bad person.
I told you, I just came to buy a senpuki.
だから 扇風機 買いにきただけだ
っつってんだろうが｡
I'd rather give it to you than hand it over to those guys.
ﾔﾂらに あれを渡すくらいなら
ｱﾝﾀのほうが ﾏｼだ｡
Will you take care of this for me?
ひとつ 頼まれてくれるかい？
おい 聞いてる？
Hey, are you listening? I said I only came to buy a senpuki.
扇風機
買いにきただけなんだってば｡
Recycled Goods Shop:
Earth Defense Army Base
Street
Liquor Store
Here
The senpuki is sealed at that address.
(娘)銭封機は
その場所に封印してある｡
I want you to go there and destroy the senpuki.
その場所に行って 銭封機を
破壊してきてほしい｡
買いにきたって言ってるﾔﾂに
破壊の申し出!?
You're telling someone who came to buy a senpuki, to destroy it?!
あれは 人心を惑わす
悪魔のｶﾗｸﾘだよ｡
It's an evil machine that destroys human souls.
人が手を出していい
代物じゃないんだ｡
It's not something people should be allowed to have.
What do you mean?
どういう意味だ？
あぁ あれか？
Are you talking about how your hand gets caught if you stick it in?
手ぇ入れたら
ｶﾞｶﾞｶﾞって引っ掛かる あれか？
痛えな…
１回は やるよな あれ…｡
That does hurt. Everyone does that at least once.
(娘)私の父は 江戸でも有数の
ｶﾗｸﾘ技師だったのさ｡
My father was one of the top mechanical engineers in Edo.
(娘)その腕に 目をつけたﾔﾂらは
父に あんなものを…｡
People sought his skills and made my father build that thing.
でも あんなものでも
父が作った 最後のｶﾗｸﾘ…｡
But it was the last machine my father ever built.
I managed to retrieve the senpuki from those men, but I was unable to destroy it this whole time.
連中から 銭封機を
取り返しておきながら➡
今まで 破壊できなかったのは➡
すべては 私の弱さゆえ…｡
All because I was weak.
あれを ﾔﾂらに渡したら
もう おしまいだわ｡
If that falls into their hands, it's all over.
So please, take that senpuki and...
お願い 銭封機を…｡
(手下)ﾌｩ～！
早く行って！
しかし…｡
Hurry and go now!
But...
江戸を… 地球を救って｡
Save Edo...and the Earth!
だ～ か～ ら！
I keep telling you, I only came here to buy a senpuki!
ｵﾚ 扇風機を
買いにきただけなんですけど～!!
Something's wrong. Very wrong!
おかしい！ 絶対 おかしい!!
扇風機を買うためにきたんだよ
ｵﾚは！
I came to buy a senpuki! So why is this happening to me?!
なのに 何をどうしたら
こうなるんだ！
待～て～！
Stop!
Hey, old man! Why is this happening to me?!
おい おっさん！
何を どうしたら こうなるんだ！
なんだ これは！ 言ってみろ!!
(おっさん)えっ？
What's going on? Tell me!
Huh? I don't know.
いや 知らないけど…｡
ｵﾚも知るか～！ ﾎﾞｹ～!!
I don't know, either! Moron!
(手下)ﾌｩ～!!
うっせぇ～！
Go to hell!
ここまできたら
もう 引き下がれるか～！
I've come too far to turn back now!!
とぉ～っ！
扇風機は…➡
The senpuki...
is mine!
ｵﾚのもんだ～！
(爆発音)
Wh-What?! Who is that guy?!
なっ… なにぃ!? 何者だ ﾔﾂは！
地球防衛軍に あんな化け物が！
Was there such a monster in the Earth Defense Army?!
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)追え！ 逃がすな！
After him! Don't let him get away!
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)なんとしても 銭封機を
手に入れるんだ～!!
We must get the senpuki at any cost!
ほわたぁ～っ！
なんだ？ ここ｡
ｶﾞﾗｸﾀばっかりじゃねえか｡
What is this place? There's nothing but junk.
扇風機～｡ 扇風機は どこだ～？
The senpuki... Where's the senpuki?!
ん？
なんだ？ この ﾊﾞｶでけえ招き猫｡
What? This huge storefront cat give me the creeps.
気味悪いな…｡
よっこいしょ…｡
Upsa. And... down...
うお～っ！ とっとっとっ…｡
(銭封機)ｾﾞﾆｬ～ｯ!!
ｺｲﾂは… 小判か？
Are these...
gold coins?
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)ﾌｯﾌﾌ｡ 驚いたかね？
Surprised, are you?
This was built by the brilliant mechanical engineering prodigy, Juttoku.
それは 天才ｶﾗｸﾘ技師
十徳が作り上げた➡
人造金貨製造器参号｡
It's the robotic gold-coin counterfeiting machine no. 3.
In other words, this is a machine that gives a reward to all of you
who worked to make the syndicate rich by minting counterfeit coins just as it planned.
We call it senpuki, for short!
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)略して 銭封機！
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)わざわざ ここまで案内
ご苦労だったな｡
Thank you for showing us the way here.
Now hand over the senpuki! You'll do it if you value your comrade's life!
銭封機を
こちらに渡してもらおう｡
同士の命が惜しくばな！
Never mind me! Quickly destroy it!
私に かまわないで！
早く それを壊して!!
…回るほうのﾔﾂは？
Where's the part that spins?
What?
はい…？
いや～ だからさ➡
I mean, not like this, but the part that whirs around...
これじゃなくて あの
ﾌﾞ～ﾝって回るほうのﾔﾂは➡
I'm asking you where that is!
どこにあるって聞いてんの～!!
(銭封機)ｾﾞﾆｬ～！
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)ｷﾞｬ～～ｯ!!
What have you done?!
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)お前
なにしてくれてんの～!?
銭封機が… それが いったい
どれだけ価値のあるものか！
The senpuki... Do you have any idea what that's worth...?
紛らわしい名前つけやがって…｡
Giving it such a confusing name!
I'll phone the JARO on you bastards.
[JARO = Japan Advertisement Review Organization]
ﾃﾒｴら ｼﾞｬﾛに電話するぞ この野郎｡
こんな汗だくになって
必死になって…➡
I'm soaking with sweat... I've had to work so hard...and even trashed my mo-ped.
原ﾁｬﾘまで おじゃんにしてよ｡
おのれ～ 地球防衛軍め…｡
Curse you... Damned Earth Defense Army! You won't get away with this!
許さんぞ！ かくなるうえは➡
Now that it's come to this, I'll use my greatest secret weapon to put an end to you.
我が最大の奥義をもって
葬り去ってくれるわ！
ﾌｯﾌｯﾌｯ｡ こんなもん…｡
This thing...
やっぱ
ｴｱｺﾝにしときゃよかったよ｡
I knew I should've bought an air conditioner.
Air conditioners are the way of the future.
これからの時代は ｴｱｺﾝだよ…｡
Oh yeah, I don't have any money.
あっ 金 ねえんだった｡
ﾊｯﾊｯﾊｯﾊｯ！ 死ねえ～!!
Die!
What?!
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰ)えぇっ!?
You...bastard!
こんちくしょう!!
(ﾘｰﾀﾞｰと手下の悲鳴)
(爆発音と悲鳴)
それっ！
Wait!
待ちなよ！ ありがとう｡
Thank you.
ｱﾝﾀ 江戸を救った英雄だよ｡
You are a hero who saved Edo.
I don't have much, but, but I do have an air conditioner at home.
(娘)お礼を…
大したもんはないけど➡
ｳﾁにあるものなら…｡
ｴｱｺﾝもあるよ｡
I don't want an air conditioner.
ｴｱｺﾝなんて いらねえよ｡
(娘)えっ？
Like I said from the beginning, I...
だからよ～
最初から言ってるだろ？ ｵﾚは…｡
Well, you know.
はい ということでな➡
It took blood and guts to get this senpuki, you see.
血の にじむような思いで
手に入れた扇風機なわけ これは｡
Look at this brilliant luster.
見ろ
この まばゆいばかりの光沢を！
Doesn't that look a little filthy?
なんか 薄汚くないですか？ それ｡
それは お前の目が
薄汚れてるからだ 新八君｡
That's because your eyes are a little filthy, Shinpachi-kun.
Now this time, use it with care so you don't break it.
いいかい？ 今度は壊さないように
大事に使うんだよ｡
いや 壊したの
ｱﾝﾀじゃないですか｡
No, you were the one who broke it.
What? What?
あれ？ あれあれ？
おかしいな… つかねえぞ｡
What? That's odd. It won't turn on.
You! I'll bet you picked that up from the dump!
ﾃﾒｴ… さては それ拾ってきたな！
大げさな作り話までしやがって！
You made up that story.
There's no Earth Defense Army.
Your story was too long!
なにが 地球防衛軍だ！
話 長えんだよ!!
Liar! You big, fat liar!
(神楽)ｳｿつき!!
この 大ｳｿつきが!!
(神楽)持ってった金
何に使ったｱﾙか！ ﾊﾟﾁﾝｺｱﾙか!!
What did you use the money you brought with you for? Pachinko?!
Ow-ow.
ｱｲﾀﾀﾀﾀ！ ちょっと待って！
ﾎﾝﾄなんだって！
Just a minute! It really is the truth!
ｵﾚ 悪の組織
やっつけたんだって！
I destroyed an evil organization!
ｵﾚ ﾎﾝﾄに
地球を救ったんだって～!!
I really did save the world!
[To Customer, from Earth Defense Army]
[The next episode: "Marriage Is Prolonging an Illusion for Your Whole Life"]
[Female ninja, Assassin Sachan, makes her appearance! Her charm points are her glasses and natto.]
[Does Gin-chan finally decide to get married? He'd better pay his respects to his future father-in-law.]
Ibaraki! Stop going to the Cabaret club so often!